welcome back everybody to the sixth
episode of active inference insights I
am back today with another fantastic
guest Adam saffron Adam is a
postdoctoral research fellow at John's
Hopkins Center for psychedelic and
Consciousness research with deep roots
in the active influence framework Adam's
work has explored the nature of
preferences and motivation mindfulness
Consciousness agency and psychedelics in
addition to this he might well be our
only guest thus far who has written a
paper titled what is orgasm and they
lifted 280 kilos for multiple reps uh in
sandals my I add uh note by the way that
these two domains need not be related
Adam thank you so much for joining me
and uh welcome to the
show so good and I'm really glad you
could join us and as I said I mean I'm
always Blown Away by the diversity of
interest and and research topics that
our guests bring to the table so it'll
be great because I think we we're going
to have a wealth of things to cover the
first thing I wanted to ask is about the
body um you write in um one of your
papers bodies represent near ideal
initial systems for Learning and
inference with this prototypical object
and causal system providing bases for
further modeling I wanted to ask because
I've been interested in what yakob how
called The evidential Boundary where can
we kind of circle off the internal and
the external uh with respect to mark of
blankets and act of inference so I
wanted to get your take on whether you
thought that what do you think of the
body is it a prior that we could say the
mind the cognitive system uh it's
incorporating uh in its in its sort of
uh predictive schema or is it itself an
objective inference that the mind um you
know conducts probabilistic reasoning
over
yes to which
one
on so I was s in that particular paper
um I'm trying to provide a count of
basically how core knowledge gets uh
loaded into Minds so you know like we
need something like core knowledge but
what's a biologically plausible account
of how we might arrive at it and so then
the idea is you're basically using um
the body as um basically a way of
structuring structuring um learning
curricula to make them tractable um for
a computationally bound system and a um
with limited learning opportunities like
making the most with the least and the
idea is you create basically the body
acts as a near um ideal like training
wheel system to figure out where the
conditions for inference are fruitfully
constrained and then you can use that in
the structureal learning process sure
and so um you can think of it as so the
body would be both um in way an
evolutionary prior and that the specific
ways in which it's some uh you know like
for instance like the um R Fifer I think
speaks really well to this in terms of
like the way that the the The Limited
shoulder the the range of what the
mobility of the shoulder Droid for
instance already would would make your
your arm go out in front of you and then
like be more likely to grab things and
where they're like well look right there
at the right distance for me to both
manipulate them and to observe them and
so those would be the kind of like
evolutionary priories you might expect
but it's like a in the bootstrapping
process it would be um you know you
could also think of it though as um like
core knowledge to get to there it would
be may maybe not necessarily an
evolutionary prior but a very reliably
learnable posterior so or an empirical
prior
um so you know I I think depending on
like but it might be so reliably learned
and so canalized uh eight ways from
Sunday that it might as well be an
evolutionary prior even though there is
like this mediation by the learning that
takes place but it's basically in the
bag because you did it because nature
did it so well um so whether you would
call it a prior or posterior um depends
on your perspective and and um some
other people who've um kind of talked to
the body is a prior like uh Micah Allen
had a good paper uh the the body is
prior talking about the way in which for
instance um our inceptive states as
particularly stubborn predictions would
help to make sure that like the whole
like generative model is basically uh
orbiting around allostasis and so like
so yeah yeah does it make does does it
make intellectual sense to you to carve
a dividing line uh like an evidential
boundary or can we is it is it more sort
of elegant to just say it's
philosophically
vague so yeah so
um so I guess like in that tradition of
like the so like the body is first prior
um there's also like to work with like
um anach andit and um others where it's
like us starting like mentalizing
homeostasis where it's like you you're
um
part of this learning curriculum is uh
multi-agent and uh coupled like like
we're starting within someone else's
bodies and then even when we're on the
outside we might as well be because
we're so dependent and so like
uh and within like this also this um um
Ral um feran context or this roboticist
um and
the overlap with like Rodney Brooks also
um similar kind of thinking with the
world is its own best model and like
emergences and more and and a lot of the
lifting being done by morphological
intelligence um you know even when you
know you're on the outside of the womb
uh you're uh intensely coupling with
others in an extended mind sense so it's
like
uh it seems like you
definitely uh you can't just say take it
like at the body boundary then you the
Mind stops you know it's um yeah this
account this is a really interesting
Avenue I've been thinking about um Clark
and charma's 98 extended mind hypothesis
paper in the lens of active inference
and I've been sort of informed in my
thinking by two people um I've really
mentioned one of them on the earlier
podcast which is Manuel delander and his
most recent book um M uh what's it
called material phenomenology he gives
us all uh mechanistic account of vision
and he critiques the an activist
tradition on this count that basically
what they want to call an intrinsic
relation I.E the coupling itself is
constitutive of the identity so in the
coupling between agent and Arena you
actually form the definition of agan
Arena he criticized it that that what
actually that really is is a causal
extrinsic relationship so that's one
strand and then the other is Thomas
metzinger and Thomas a did a podcast
with professor friston and he spoke
about how the notion of inaction might
be quite misleading because it kind of
implies that there is there might be a
subtle reoc of a cartisian ego where you
have a enacting b so I want you know I
want to kind of pick your brain on that
because it's interesting you B up
extended cognition and the fact that the
Mind might its identity might go beyond
the the remits of the
body are we are we at in danger there
invoking what danda calls an intrinsic
Rel relation where really what we're
looking at is just causal connections uh
and we're not we shouldn't actually be
mistaking that for identity
relations I'm not sure um and and you
know I might also um like in that paper
I imagine I like kind of antagonize more
than a few people and actually of like
going uh neoc cartisian in a way like
suggesting like something like quasi
homuncular and thees is like as like a
ways of like understanding like agents
and their relations to the world in
terms of like the way they're situated
and that um internal having an
internalized
representation uh pegged according to
this uh reference frame of an observer
um from an ego Centric perspective uh
would do a lot of like heavy lifting in
the process of structure learning and
making things tractable um so
um the yes it's like I guess yeah you
might have to like loop around a few
times you know in terms getting me to
dock properly but uh I guess the way I'm
thinking it's like like mind as model
has to be like extended and it's like
the
um the ways in which like the affordance
landscape is so dependent on these
couplings to to like to to go to
internalist is in a way miss the point
about what lets you do anything what
lets your natur but I I do have
sympathies for the internalist account
in terms of making room for things like
um representation so that you can do
things like um offline learning and
imaginative planning and like you know
basically like the world is its own best
model whenever possible it's
morphological compute a compute you know
uh emergent com um Mor uh you know
from the couplings of the organism
environment you put don't just like push
your predictions down to to the lowest
level of like the brain push them out
into the environment yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah well EXA I mean yes that that I
guess was the the question I wanted to
come to which is um so it's all very
nicely
interwoven you're right you invoke this
notion of the kind of Quasi hular
systems um and you mentioned the frame
problem um which is a really interesting
problem to me which is kind of how can
we be uh intelligent in an ignorant
manner uh how can we zero in on personal
information in the world given the
preponderance of sense data intelligent
in an ignorant manner I love that um
thanks it's it's it's uh it's not mine
I'll shout out John vvi I mean he's the
one who's kind of outlined the frame
problem to me more than more than anyone
else you so I this is kind of a leading
question because I have a sense of where
you're going to how you're going to
answer it given what you just said
but can the frame problem be solved by
just kind of a single conscious
homunculus at the tip of the prefontal
cortex and if not how deep do these or
how deep do you imagine that these quasi
homuncular or non all these mindless
cognitive agents as manand would call
them how deep do they go towards the
skin I'm sorry I don't I've gone right
into the deep end on these but why not
no no it's good
um so it's seems
like
the extended and active
nature of Minds um helps to curtail like
frame problems and that you're you're
always like in the world in particular
ways and if like you're coupling with
the environment is creating basically
like is basically like in a way creating
like an enslaving Center manifold for
the whole system that you you you always
have to keep coming back to to stay on
top of this action not just to stay on
top of this action perception cycle and
on top of um this inter interchange um
you know the full scope of relevance as
if you're always kind of like being
brought back home and
grounded in this common task of cyber
control that that seems to like take
some of like the I I don't if it quite
defangs the frame problem but it helps
to curtail it a bit um the and so then
you know but in terms of also like
taking the the the range of um you know
potential relevant affordances it's
still you know a big space um but still
you know the idea of like orbiting it
around
um an agent's model of itself and
interaction with the world
um I don't know how far um homuncular
for instance representation gets you
with respect to that but in a way it um
the idea of like basically one of the
core things that you're modeling is the
living body the idea at the center of
your experience this um uh you know so
so the hun I guess so guess unpack hun
so like the the thing that people are
worried about would be right a
homuncular regress where just like
there's a little man in the head that's
doing the observing and you've explained
things and so the reason I kind of um
start to push on this issue of like
trying to resurrect homunculi and things
like cartisian theaters is the idea is
that the the folk intuition and and like
is coupled to the phenomenology in a way
that actually might reflect the data
structures might actually reflect the um
way the system is organ reflect the
principles of the controller right
and and so um you know the importance of
taking your perception and giving it a
coherent perspectival reference frame so
something you know theater esque in
terms of you know um having like the
right geometric relations of the things
of the world their relationship to you
but then also for instance though the
idea of like an observer that helps that
watches the screen um the sense of um
your embodiment as a central dat
structure um being in close uh
communication uh with uh basically uh
the systems by which you would do a
visual perceptual synthesis because you
know you're um you know what your body
is doing will inform what you're likely
to be what it means what's coming in on
your Rea and or the visual spatial Sy
the somata spatial should tell you about
the Visos spatial and vice versa and
it's interesting that in robotics these
are actually the primary data structures
they so like in the collaborations um
I've done with like Tim ver Bale and and
oen Catal like um in their latent slam
systems one of the primary things for
situating the robot in the world is
basically a conjunction of views and
poses it's like and and they're almost
like one data structure and that it's
you know one of the best you know where
I'm looking you know where where I'm
where my sensors are oriented are going
to be highly informative for what I'm
looking at and also just where my the
way my body is configured um I don't
think this quite gets in this isn't
quite brought into their systems but you
know the range of relevant importances
what am I like be seeing well your the
your uh what your body is doing will be
highly relevant to that also and so the
mutual information should be very strong
closely coupled right yeah it it it it
kind of brings me back to the to the
first question I guess which is I mean I
could probably reward that now using the
terms you just said I mean I think
internal and external an act of
inference can be considered a a kind of
relative
misnomer um because if you know I I like
Maxwell's rewording of it as uh tracking
and tracked or modeling and modeled I
think that's quite an effective way of
resif in the focus here so I guess the
way of reording that question is you
know are we in invoking a homunculus and
the C in theater are we a risk therefore
of kind of thinking that there's a a
genuine ontological homunculus
which is conducting variational Basi and
inference uh and and and has a model um
over which it does
computations I think like that rubs a
lot of people the wrong way because for
a lot of people it's just dynamical
systems um and so you know do these
kinds of questions actually call into
question the more
fundamental um dichotomy of tracking and
tracked and distinct ontologies distinct
entities in the
world potentially um and
the so you know maybe I'm asking for too
much but I want to have it all I want to
have um
I an active couplings in the streets and
like reations and at Sheets you know
like um you know to the extent possible
like you know there's even need to
appeal to like some sort of model
representation for much of what I'm
describing of this like Mutual
contextualization of like these
different sensory systems in terms of
they're already coordinated just by
having a certain situation on the body
itself and in the world and the way like
the um the the information is cascading
in the context of the inactive coupling
and so there there's a sense you know
the the the model of the agent is
extended into the world its mind is
extended already there and a lot of like
the the work I'm talking about we like
the homonculus is the body itself
there's no need for like an in addition
representation of it um I do though
suggest we might have though um you know
such basically a uh a data structure you
would say or um and and maybe even
um potentially
involving
uh you know I I I put this forward
basically as a kind of pred
that like nothing rides on in the sense
of
like uh if I'm wrong sure uh but if I'm
right could be interesting so but the
specific idea is that there might be sub
networks of the brain that actually um
have a geometric organization about them
in terms of you might you would even
have like within cortical Hub structures
potentially a
um geometric
correspondences through the manifold
activity in those networks and what's
being represented so you you could even
get like homuncular in terms of like the
network is almost little personlike on
some portions and the reason you might
want to do this is that um within
geometric deep learning like if you give
a network the same geometry essentially
um not like a physical Network in terms
of
like well guess it would be there in the
connect eventually but like it could be
just like a dynamic emerging pattern um
effective connectivity but like if the
the network though has the same
structure as that which which it is um
representing or modeling or trying to
track you end up getting potentially
orders of magnitude greater
efficiency yeah that's really cool
that's really so it's it's possible that
like there could be in addition to like
most of what we're doing is like
effortless Mastery and the vular story
you never need representation you never
need internalized model and most of it's
and you would want that too you know
that's right that's quicker more
efficient but you might also on top of
that for the sake of things like
imaginative planning things like having
more nuanced control of the sensory
motor engagement you might also have
representations of this um and um
potentially even uh uh shockingly
cartisian accounts like in terms of
Highly centralized and even kind of
looking uh with a GE ometry that would
that would be uh of a similar shape to
the body itself yeah that that's
fascinating I mean these uh these
strange Loops as hofstead would call
them are are seemingly never ending the
body having Loops of itself the body
having Loops of the world I mean it
comes back to I think um kind of the
cybernetic good regulator theorum and
and like is that saying you know there's
this kind of confusion is that saying
that all good Regulators have a model of
the world or are a model of the world
and I think I think I don't know I mean
I don't know whether you think that's
still a Live question in active
inference I mean to be honest to be
completely candid and yes I'm a relative
Layman with a Year's experience of
thinking about active inference and not
understanding the maths and the physics
but that's okay I think there's still a
kind of question there which is and Cole
to be honest was quite neutral on on it
when I asked him which is like what is
it
what what will are internal
States um yes internal so so it makes
sense that internal states have or
embody have embodi beliefs about the
external States I mean that is at the
heart of like a likelihood mapping so
fine but is that it uh is that what
we're going to give them is these
beliefs and what is it to embody a
subpersonal belief is it just an
instantiate like I think people find it
very difficult to basically move away
from the physical mechanics to the
statistical mechanics and I think there
needs to be a bridging mechanism so I
don't know if you had any thoughts just
on like the broader way that a sort of
layman audience including myself could
make those intuitive or those
non-intuitive distances between
statistics and physic or the physical
Material World a bit more
intuitive
like we're working with this account of
like you know blankets of blankets of
blankets and
um I guess the way I'm interpreting is
like a
um
internal internal States course graining
external States and then Nest within
there internal States course graining
external States so on and so forth like
a an a hierarchy or a hierarchy of
nested nested blanketed structures um
you know giving you the these multiple
levels of resolution that you can unpack
as needed and so I guess the the thing
I'm wondering is whether like
uh I like I wonder
whether a uh all so so it seems like you
know none of it works without like the
inactivist principles like without like
the um the the the structuring of what's
Happening by intelligent morphologies or
um or without just like that um uh the
nature of the coupling of the system in
this world providing like the grounding
and the semantics um and the interest
none of it gets off the ground but but
the story still it can be told just just
at the level of like the system and its
extended phenotype as this one single
model and like where do you draw this
boundary what's internal what's external
it's like it depends on the scale you're
thinking about it right um and so I
guess the place where I wonder is where
going to need internalism is when we get
to Consciousness yes basically like so
so like so I guess you might even call
me like a kind of like pan psychist of a
stripe and psyche in terms of understood
as like mind but then when you get to
like basically Consciousness in terms of
something like uh a system for we might
say there is something that it feels
like to be that system then and for that
can do things like um imagine for
instance in dream like for for that and
those elements of experience it seems
like we're going to have to at some
point invoke um enough uh a a a a we're
going to need a blanket uh uh a a set of
attractors that are
internal and can uh basically Break Free
of the immediate engagement with the
world that's part of our experience and
so like for people I think to actually
like account for phenomenology to
account for like you know like a the
things that that matter to us you know
eventually getting to you know things
like agency even like free will we're
going to need to at some point um go
internalist but like in that process
though you know it's just but uh still
the story for most of evolution uh you
know but still like if you go in that
direction though and you lose sight of
the the inactivist principles well then
you you basically find yourself in the
same places that I guess you could say
like the mainstream uh machine learning
goes astray
sometimes you think you're going to
handle the problem just with scale or
raw compute or or you don't understand
like the kinds of uh learning curricula
you would need to bootstrap intelligence
systems or how they would need to be
deployed to to you know achieve goals in
the world um so uh yeah so again like I
I think I end up like occupying a very
awkward position that's like you know
the um radical and activists will be
like
you know you don't need to invoke these
things like um uh uh cogn this might be
like you know I know you're leaning way
too hard and saying that like embodiment
is necessary and and you're just and but
I think that is the case though like
it's the
um I think everyone was kind of right in
just like emphasizing account of what's
going on yeah yeah yeah I mean I I I
haven't St my my personal claim but I
don't disagree and I think that Nuance
is is is always going to be right in
some fundamental sense um all theories
are wrong they're just wrong at
different you know to different degrees
all metaphors are wrong some metaphors
are useful right exactly I mean I I was
Wonder you know it's funny that it's not
funny it's interesting that you say that
the an activist principles are
necessary um it'd be great to have like
a pure inter or I can't label people but
like someone like yob Howie who you know
if he was here might again I'm not
putting words in his mouth so it be
curious to see what he thinks might ask
whether
it's uh
conceivable that a kind of compute only
system could do variational Basi and
inference um given its priors I mean I
think I think another useful distinction
actually to to unpack for our audience
and something that I found really really
useful is this distinction between uh
having a sort of
epistemically viable model model of the
world so you are actually you know it's
descriptive it it accounts for the
sensations that it's uh observing or it
sensation it's receiving and a
normatively viable model of the world
I.E one where you aren't just dispersing
into the heat B but you can maintain
your own sort of autopoetic
organization and I'm wondering whether
you think it's conceivable to any degree
whether both sides of that equation
could be fulfilled by
a kind of sheltered off super
intelligent
homunculus sheltered off and it never
comes into contact well I mean so so it
it comes into contact uh vicariously
through the markup
blanket so so there I I'll permit active
and sensory States
um but again vicariously it has to do
this kind of variational basin inference
um based on its its model and we can
kind of get into the maths of that a
little bit of like where that model
comes from in the first
place might not be quite what I think
we're we're driving at but like one
thing I would wonder in terms of like um
like saying like no you don't need um um
you know things like uh active learning
to be like intell
to you don't need to
like invoke things like extended mind
Concepts you don't need to invoke things
like Niche construction like in theory
like you could do everything just from
like
uh a smart enough basing Observer like I
guess would that be like the complete
class Ser is like like like uh well yes
like almost like has to be the case but
that that in theory you could do it that
the the an activist um elements that
being appealed to like if you're going
like in theory if you want to like build
like a like an AGI or something uh you
wouldn't need to but then I guess the
question is like if that in theory
though like in theory like a three layer
neural network can compute anything
right question it just might have to be
so big it doesn't fit in like the
universe and so it's like if that in
theory can't become in
practice given like available compute
available to systems we would real we
would feasibly be able to create then it
becomes I think a little bit moot
although still interesting about like
that case of like uh like is it a matter
of in principle or in practice so um
yeah it's where philosophy has its
limits perhaps um where conceivability
arguments have their limits you know a
question that popped up into my mind is
boot strapping up uh intelligent uh or
you know um kind of inv vitro
intelligence um I think I think one
question I've always had is the priors
that um are encoded in the generative
model kind of make sense in this
normatively viable sense so people just
think of homeostasis we have these kinds
of um yeah prior expectations about the
states that we expect to be in and will
act accordingly to to confirm that model
I think people might have a bit of a
difficulty applying the same logic to um
perceptual inference so perceptual
inference uh you know this idea that
basically you're inverting Bay you are
trying to derive the state from the
observation I guess the the question
that I have is if that's a sort of P of
x given y your your probability of the
state given the observation obviously
that's done through some form of the
variational base people might be asking
well where does the p of X comes from
where does your prior of
States before observations
um I think what might be the denter in
pom DPS where does that come from like
is that encoded in the fenot type in the
same way that homeo
homeostatic uh imperatives might
be or yeah or is it the the D Matrix or
the like you know I think it's the yeah
I think it's the D Matrix again I'm not
a computation by your specific
initialization within the environment
and like getting the ball rolling the
yes exactly exactly it's you know
it so it's
like it seems like it's like we know
like without the inductive biases like
none of it works the structural learning
is just impossible you know with without
the evolutionary priors without like
some sort of like you know intelligent
initialization I guess the place where
um I tend to have a I guess like a
heterodox View and that like it's like
well I grant like we need something like
core knowledge we need basically prior
to to lean on um I tend to think that um
EV like natural selection had fat
fingers when it came to like like doing
the design like both in terms of like
potential complexity mismatches between
inherited information and then like what
comes afterwards but also due to like in
like not just like in
uh why you know people sometimes refer
to like the difference and complexity
between like the genome and the
connectome for instance you know but
obviously you know the genome you the
epome and there's a lot more inheritance
than that like just in like the cell
like a lot there's a lot of inheritable
elements that that go off so the
question is like but even then there
does seem to be some difference in like
you've squeezed through the bottleneck
of like an ovom and so from this one
cell you reconstituted the rest and this
kind of like kind of like Auto encoding
like you get to pass through a
bottleneck here and somehow but from
this you're now though going to con
reconstitute a a network of effective of
functional relations and effective
connections like a full like brains
connectum and is you know is there
enough in there to likey things the way
you might need to um the way I tend to
like kind of think about it is like so
one heuristic is um you know the more so
like what um kind of knowledge might
might we need what might be the nature
of the representation or just the
instantiation Al then the more complex
it is the less likely it is that that is
in a more direct sense uh specified by
so it's like yeah you know if we're
talking about like you know um so for
instance like you can think of like uh
there's like a prior encoded for
instance in like the the Frog brain of
like the superior calculus of like
potentially of um based on sensitivities
to luminance it might help like zoom in
on eyes potentially like that could be
example of something or or um prior
about like where you expect light to be
coming from in general and this like
helps to make things tractable but then
let's say you're talking about some of
like know good oldfashioned evolutionary
psychology like at The Other Extreme
like a you know like a cheater detection
module well how the heck would you do
that right yeah yeah yeah so it's like
how um likely is it that you could
basically in this learning
curriculum have these lessons occur and
have this knowledge we acquired uh early
enough and the simpler it is the more
likely it could be there early um that
there's um a meaningful degree of
canalization that is actually part of
natural selection right right right in
general the uh
uh claim I've been making is that
uh in order to pull this off um a lot of
it was indirect even for a lot of the
the core knowledge people will appeal to
um that you basically just needed to
create a tractable learning curriculum
to get there and what natural selection
was primarily doing was sculpting
learning
curricula using like uh the the the body
and its positioning as a large source of
Leverage on this to help um reliably
acquire the knowledge you need but it
it's still though acquired but but and
how much the adap is able to do that
would be depend would be um the the the
simpler it is
the more likely you could meaningfully
make that a canalization pathway yeah
yeah that that's awesome that's that's a
great way of looking at it I it's funny
my undergrad was in linguistics um and
Linguistics was the was the hot bed for
all of this stuff you know I mean chonky
really um chonky and chomsky's Darwin's
Darwin problem I mean this is like what
he was talking about in the 90s and he
had to sort of pair down what Universal
grammar was because the big question was
okay you can account for you know
perhaps principles and parameters
can account for the complexity and
creativity of language learning but how
the hell are these hundreds of
parameters going to be encoded in the
genome like in like the versions of like
CH skin thinking where he's going
minimalist talking about something like
yeah recursion yeah so then if it's just
like something like merge it's like well
sure that seems very plausible right
right right right even quickly in
evolution like the ways it's been
suggested you know and part of like what
correspond to like these like phase
transitions we see where all of a sudden
and like new orders are coming on pretty
compressed intervals yeah but but yeah
but if you're going to like you know the
other limit like things like I guess
like a I don't know Pinker and like yes
so then it's like uh oh that I'm not
sure biology can do that well I think he
made I think he made that concession um
Chomsky at least I'm not sure about
Steven Pinker but Chomsky certainly does
and as you say has a minimist program
with merge um but yeah I think a law
linguist might argue that he's uh he's
kind of abandoned that native this
project um but anyway we need not go in
there I'll try and get him on the Pod
actually um sticking on sort of
evolution my background is not an
evolutionary biology or psychology so
I'm I'm super Keen to learn um again
just to take a quote of yours um you say
much of the functional significance of
specific Connections in complex neural
networks maybe inherently difficult to
predict due to the sensitivity of
brackets chaotic self org izing systems
to initial conditions so when I hear
that I think sure like it certainly
makes sense in terms of initial
volatility probably having more of an
effect on self-organization than once
you have a kind of robust
phenotype but why therefore is there a
convergence within a species a phenotype
to kind of a homogeneity if there is
this kind of vulnerab ability to um to
chaos it seems like a good amount of it
I mean that that a good you know to
get so you're having a system which
has um that's massively recurrent in
terms of like it's like in it in the
system as it develops it feeds back on
itself and then that influences Fe back
on itself and that influences and so
there's this potential for
amplifications to take you in a lot of
different directions but natural
selection doesn't want you to go in any
given Direction it wants that
homogeneity it wants you to be like well
fit to be you know uh have high Fitness
he wants you to be fit to your uh the
the niches you're likely to be
encountering and to be able to you know
survive
and proliferate your forms in those
circumstances and so you know you don't
want be just like open you want that
homogeneity but the process because it
feeds back on itself will be um it
should have this potential for
uh astronomical bifurcation so how do
you like reain it
in you know there seems
like and so know you could just say like
you know well that's what the inductive
biases are and so you know let there be
inducted biases and it was good right
but but well which ones and how and so I
wonder the extent to which like
a choke
points
for um
coordination among subelements of the
system such as for instance like any
kind of place you could identify
something like a bow TI Motif any place
where you can get something like
a large sale convergence Divergence
which in general you would expect
because you need small worldness for the
sake of just efficiently getting a
system to be integrated or to have a
system be integrated all that you know
you want to be able to have the
different components function together
but if everything's wired if
everything's connected to everything
that's both chaos and there's there's no
uh it's very inefficient so the idea of
like these places where things uh uh
from Broad sense will pass
through then providing basically an
opportunity for um
enslavement system so um so some of this
could just be uh Network motifs like you
look at um for instance um convergence
onto like Hub structures that have high
centrality but also things like if you
take the value signals like you know
things like uh dopamine or serotonin and
you um have those also have a um the
conditions of their release correspond
to organism scale events then that could
help basically um give coordination to
the overall system in reliable ways for
this task of uh helping the organism
make it through the world helping it to
helping the system to function so it's
like these these these codependencies
and from and choke points the these um
places where you'll get um uh functional
convergence I I I suspect that's like um
important for
keeping that Divergence from happening
too much this uh uh integration into
organismic significance of with respect
to cybernetic control of the agent
pursuing its goals and and if that has
perched if that basically by virtue of
whether we're talking about like value
signals that would then you know shape
connections um or or or the the
structure of the architecture itself if
that is positioned such that the whole
system can be so enslaved that that
should help to like even though that
should basically help these bifurcations
in a way be uh not bugs but features and
that it's sort of like they're sources
of like solenoidal flow and expirations
and like uh you know engaging like local
pockets of like high temperature search
but then like you rein it back in for
staying on top of the action perception
cycle and so to kind of come back to
like Consciousness know for me um it's
basically iterative State
estimation with s with the goal being
basically I want to know a Rough and
Ready estimate of the relationship
between the system and the world
generated quickly enough that I can
meaningly inform and be informed by
action perception Cycles on the time
scale of their formation and so I can
Nuance that engagement provide some
extra skillful control and surfing
uncertainty so it's like um and so like
if the primary like task of the system
is this inactive coupling I feel like
that helps to provide that um uh that's
helps to like tame and harness chaos
rather having the thing sort of uh
bifurcate in in you know all the like
hyper astronomical number of Dimensions
it could go cool yeah yeah yeah there's
a lot there I mean yeah let's uh let's
do the Consciousness thing um I was
going to jump psychedelics but like why
don't we start even more fundamental
Consciousness uh anyone who's watched
the first five episodes or four episodes
knows that I love Consciousness uh it
was kind of my for into all of this so
what you've given me there is a a
function of Consciousness it's guiding
action perception Loops it's it's it's
kind of a likelihood mapping State
estimation okay but as you can imagine
the follow-up question is going to be
why does it come with its phenominal
characteristics um um is there something
that's intrinsic is there something
that's adapt
to those phenomenal characteristics
which facilitate improve augment the
function that you've just laid
out I think you know people could still
you know like you know
uh yeah
hold
there's why can't these functions you
know all take place in the dark why must
they like feel like anything at all
I I I don't think that that concern is
removed I think it loses some of its
Force if the nature of the uh data
structure is considered as being like
specifically the generation of a visual
spatial and somat spatial field of
experience
um Precision weighted or having like
with biases rather
like different areas of salience and
emphasis based on organismic need and
like if you're basically taking like
basically the the the the thing you are
estimating is the sensorium
itself it sort of like well it feels
like something because like emphasis on
the feels like like what the data
structure is a specifically an inversion
of a generative model over the sensorium
of embodied aded agent so that's
actually what the process is
specifically doing now you can still say
well why couldn't you do the state
estimation of the system in the world in
the dark
exactly you know I think it's that
objection though so the claim is that
objection holds more for theories of
Consciousness that forget we have bodies
so you could still Levy it but I think
it's like slightly addressed by making
the primary
explanandum the uh appearance of a world
to a lived body if that is the primary
explanatum and you're specifically
saying how might Dynam DCS um compute
that then I think it it it takes that on
a little bit more the why should there
be something at feels like because what
you're specifically trying to explain is
the fields itself right it sounds to me
quite convergent with Mark SS's sort of
AFF effect driven account of
qualia this being that sort of these
fundamental effective states are um are
sort of guides in a way
to um allostatic Behavior so whether
that's the resolution of
uncertainty um Information Gain um
testing model parameters or actually
just minimizing variational fre energy
see that for me was one of the first
functional explanations of Consciousness
that really made me think oh that's
that's kind of viable because I can't
conceive of a feeling without it being
felt um and so what I've been looking
for
is these kind of um it's almost like a
synthetic a priori of Consciousness it's
almost like a transcendental argument
for Consciousness does anything like
Circle back on itself so as to make
Consciousness a prerequisite for the
function and I think where you and Mark
are converging here is quite promising
which is that now someone like David oh
what someone like 1995 David Charmers
might go well you could just have like
an offline signal that says things are
uncertain and let's resolve that
uncertain
granted but then I take quite seriously
this uh this older phenomenological hyan
idea that like we're being to take a
stance on our own existence and that's
got to be felt to some degree um so I'm
wondering what you think of of of that
Spiel and perhaps where there's a points
of convergence with with Marx homes's
theories I'd say um very strong place of
convergence but also Divergence okay the
convergence is like
you know he's um he he's bringing in
life mind continuity he's bringing in
like the necessary interestedness of the
system and also like the the primary
nature
of of affect and of saying like and like
you're saying like this synthetic op
like like what do we need to even
coherently conceive of this thing where
like what's foundational like if you
were to doubt it the whole like game
Falls apart exactly yeah so unless you
have like unless we get the feels in
there we're not getting anywhere and
unless we get like the
um you know and so the the I guess the
thing I would
suggest uh as as a point of Divergence
uh would be I wonder if the specific
systems so so I guess like for for me um
I don't necessarily take
unconscious feelings to be an
oxymoron but um you know so we can use
words differently but sometimes I'll
I'll think of like one way of thinking
of like emotions and feelings almost
like a very abstract action perception
cycle where it's like the emotions are
the global State changes I don't I don't
think it I think by the time you get to
that level abstraction the difference
between action perception falls apart
but in a way though like the the the the
the change in organismic mode to be
adaptive for a particular class of
situations whatever that is that seems
to be roughly something like a motion
would correspond to this and where the
organismic mode could extend beyond the
organism in terms of the emotion just
like contained within it but the feeling
part potentially being some sort of um
uh inference on top of that process
right some sort of TR tracking of that
now we can use words in any way but like
I would personally um so that's that's a
that's the way I think of it and the way
I describe think of in that entropy
paper and then I wonder where we whether
we can have both unconscious and
conscious feelings and emotions yeah
like level where like you know we go
back down to the individual cell and the
cell is like changing into like a spor
related mode and maybe that's like it
becoming afraid or something or it like
extends a pillis to like exchange a
chromosome someone else you know whether
that chromosome a a chromatid and that's
like maybe like a lust mode or like it
releases you know exotoxins or that's
like a like like a aggression mode or
something like a rage mode like and so
like I I like the idea of like you know
kind like the work of like damasio who
like Mark like engaged with in in
beautiful ways like you
know the you know I I I love this idea I
think it's essential for understanding
like the actual cybernetic significance
of feelings and emotions to actually be
coherent about them to actually talk
about life mind continuity and to
recognize this is an older story than
even nervous systems in terms of like
the the the um the harmonics or the the
igen modes of the org of the organism to
be adaptive having those to be uh uh to
give them an overall coherent shape but
uh for the specific systems that Mark
talks about um I wonder whether they uh
I guess uh have what it takes to do the
kind of like representation game whether
um they're um potentially doing their
functioning um so so emphasize like the
perac Dual
gray and and as you know being this um
integration around organism of need and
this sort of like the way that um um
aexs in order for them to in order for
these igen mode shifts to be coherent so
that you're you're not like eating and
doing Care at the same time you know
like that would be a bad idea a lot of
circumstances like you know you don't
want like you know mothers to eat their
pups you know you don't want like this
um picking and the I think I don't if he
says color coding but this like
categorical breakdown yes I'm totally
with him functionally but it still
seemed like those could happen in the
dark right and so the thing I'm
wondering is in order for them to be
given something like phenomenality that
we experience of like the conscious
feelings I'm wondering whether that
requires something like
um basically a re-representation into
cortical circuits and so he'll um
and maybe even within uh within samat
spatial and Visos spatial modalities so
I make a uh someone considered would
consider to be a bizarre claim that
those might actually be all we have and
all other modalities are basically uh
kind of synesthetically cross mapped
into those to be given spatial and and
temporal spatial coherence so that they
actually can be modeled and you can do
this like State estimation so the idea
of like your inter receptive States
might actually be
to be experienced have to be spatialized
as a kind of like texture or as a kind
of like like I I feel I I have to I have
to temporize and spatialize that
information and maybe part of the way
you do it is to unfold them into another
modality as part of the inference so
um but
the
uh yes so I guess the difference with
is I'm wondering
whether his account is
like like like right on on the
functional level but um the systems
though that would actually but still
though the systems he's emphasizing
would be necessary but not sufficient
conditions in order to obtain
sufficiency they need to basically um
enslave cortical circuits and that those
might actually be the constitutive
causal um the constitutive realizers of
experience potentially by virtue of the
fact that like again we I guess we get
to like things like small worldness um
networks that are basically collocated
enough that they can Converge on
attractors and a cheap
coherence on the right time scale the
idea of like if you're like way far so
the idea is like if you're way far away
from like let's say like some sort of
rhythmic attractor over um uh uh is
established that's um calculating
something like your sensorium or like
entailing something like the inversion
of your sensorium on the time scales at
which that sensorium is inverted um
there might be an in and an out in terms
of like who is able to get their message
in a time and it's possible that the
systems he's identifying could be um on
the outside of it in terms of the time
skills at which that cause of closure
occurs while still being completely
necessary for their functioning I I just
don't think we know and so the evidence
is you know he would then push back and
then say like you know oh well um the uh
let's see uh well no you know I I leion
the insula And the emotions are still
there so there's yourway and there's
it's like yes um but
uh I guess in a way you you might say
that that that somewhat supports the the
that quasi synesthetic account I just
said but um I basically I I find the
lines of evidence that are cited to be
um not but none of them are quite
convincing to me so like so for instance
like um uh uh like hydralic children
like yeah you know they're still showing
these rich emotive explains but the
issue is though uh we don't know yeah
like it could be unconscious emotional
you we can't ask them we don't know to
like from the inside or then you might
point to like um like decorit rodents
showing Like You Know Rich like you know
adaptive emotional uh responses and and
sophisticated behaviors but once again
we don't know um or you might like drop
an electrode and then stimulate these
subcortical areas and then you get
experience and the person reports to
them but then the problem is well the
cortex is intact then and so how do you
know if when you Dro that electrod like
you stimulate the hypothalamus and then
you got some sort of Rage response or a
lust response was it that that was the
realizer or is it as I'm suggesting that
that was basically um part of um you
know it it was uh causally important for
the whole thing to work but not
necessarily constitutive of the process
that um computes or realizes the the
quails so this is cool this is cool yeah
I feel like there are two things going
on and I'd like to sort of see if we can
converge them so one is a kind of
structural functional description which
which is
augmenting um or just providing color to
Mark's view which is that we need these
kind of uh recursive Loops back to the
cortex it needs to enslave the you know
the these subcortical structures need to
enslave the cortex now someone listening
might go but that's just a
further functional structural anatomical
explanation on the other hand you invoke
kind of
Proto back to the homunculi these kind
of Proto conscious agents we got like
whether that's a cell a cluster of cells
and so
on and you've spoken as well about how
you know one of your your account of
Consciousness you know can be cast as a
convergence of active inference and
integrated information
Theory um in you know integrated
information the go some well it got some
bad press earlier this year for being
pseudo science um on for those listening
just on audio I am doing speech marks um
but one of the claims was that it was
pandering in some sense to pans
psychism and perhaps an uh aute listener
might be thinking oh Adam is maybe
pandering attached to panm with his idea
of lustful uh
neurons where do your sympathies lie if
we take this sort of broader
philosophical position um where do your
sympathies lie with pan psychism and
let's just say more kind of uh I think
they're called conscious realist
positions such as that of Donald Hoffman
for
example I'll regret saying this but I
think you could call me a pan psychist
of swords still and that like um other
sense of um anything that's somehow
managed to thing and coming back to the
good regulator theorem on some level had
to entail some sort of modeling
information whether it was this the
system and it's interaction with the
environment was the model or is a is a
model that within it has models um but
has to have um some sort of tracking or
predictive
information uh
that allows it to basically reverse
resist the most uh temporarily uh res um
uh defy the second law while serving in
everything it does but basically that
you know you getting all mixed up and
becoming maximally probable maximum ENT
R distribution like how did you do that
you someh did something to do that yeah
sort of intelligence some sort of thing
like a mly some sort of predictive
information had to have been there for
you to pull off something a little bit
like Maxwell demon demon esque you know
to to do that and so and that since like
I'd say I'm a pan psychist and that like
anytime we're pointing to things anytime
there's attractors um you might want to
say there's something mind-like going on
something a little bit intelligent um
but the um you might even want to say
like some psychological kinds you know
like like we're talking about with like
talking about like the individual cells
you know Rage or lust you know um like
even those might be like good ways of
thinking about them in terms of
describing their cybernetic significance
like it's a you know coherent Global
change of state with a certain semantics
that's linked to modeling and so if you
think of you know mind as modeling and
then as modeling with interest and EV
Valu l in way you know you might call
that sentience then but I guess I want
to reserve this word Consciousness for
the it feels like something and I want
to Res and and there's there's something
that you know it feels like from the
inside to be that system and you so all
these systems would have a kind of uh
dual aspect part to them because they
would entail an information geometry and
so you can say it's like well you know
maybe everything that exists it's just
like that's the way of describing the
dual aspect nature of them um I think
you can make a case for that but I still
want though like um
basically um okay so in in so integr
World modeling Theory the thing I
attempted was to um take the major
theories um specifically focusing on
integrated information Theory and the
global workspace Theory and then
basically use you could say probability
Theory or machine learning or this the
free energy principle this idea of the
system modeling its environment
probabilistically as now providing the
semantics and removing the question
begging from these theories in terms of
or Su of it of why there should be
something that it's like to be a complex
of integrated information or to be the
um to have Fame in the brain and to be
within a global workspace yeah so why
well if what that global workspace is
doing is it's something like a very
efficient
architecture um for all for like some
you know autoencoding hierarchy if it's
like an arena for basian model selection
allowing for this iterative state
estimation well then we know we're the
questions are somewhat less begged or if
like integr information theory is
describing you know um uh the nature of
networks that can do interesting forms
of compute it's like okay um you know
necessary conditions you know likely you
know in information the they they have
these these axioms they're that they
look at that apply purportedly to all
conscious experiences and then they try
to identify these Mech they postulate
mechanisms that could realize them and
then the idea is like if you start out
going from these axium of char
experience you then create a precise and
specific mapping to particular
mechanisms that would be that would
allow for their realization now you can
say this system's conscious and that one
isn't and maybe even this system is
conscious in that way and not that way
and you know I think it's it's really
promising but but the issue um I take is
um uh basically um in a way like like
losing the explanandum
of uh our sensorium our our sensory our
sense world you know our embodied
experience and so if what that uh if
what a complex of integrated information
is doing is it's basically describing a
system set up for a certain type of
Dynamics within it that could enable a
certain type of um message passing and
um and and inference and you know belief
propagation inference and specifically
with the thing being entailed by such a
system would be the you know efficient
inversion of a sensorium over uh
inversion of a generative model over the
sensorium of embodied by an agent now
we're getting somewhere so for so the
idea is saying okay um uh so I guess I'm
sympathetic to both sides and viewing
integrated information Theory as um
having some elements which are
unsatisfactory
um
the but you know I don't think it was
that particularly I don't think what
happened was particularly helpful in
terms of Pudo science and you know
uh for a variet of reasons but so so
yeah so the basic approach is this what
if you um take the existing theories the
major ones cross reference their claims
look for points of overlap and try to
use basically degree of convergence and
the forms of convergence and the
coherence of those stories to adjudicate
among different claims and so that was
the basic method and so um you could
think of for instance um you know
integrated information Theory will talk
about um potentially there's a a
posterior Hot Zone as the substrate of
Consciousness and you know for instance
I say that sounds about right that for
instance like you know if basically the
posterior if you take these different
sensory hierarchies all coming together
into one multi hierarchy and if you can
get um basically across that system its
ability to uh loop back on itself in a
very powerful way in a very um you know
both integrated but also differentiated
way then that could be that then you
could think of that is basically um that
that could entail the inversion of of a
gener model over the sensorial of an EMB
body and B agent maybe that's what's
going on you could also potentially
think of though this complex of integr
information that has both uh integration
that where the network properties are
set up to facilitate both integration
and differentiation that's actually has
a lot of correspondences to workspaces
which mountains integrated segregated
functioning and so the ideaas like that
poster hassum could be thought of as a
fairly Global
workspace you know and um with devils in
details of exactly the kind of workspace
it is and you know with um with me
having some specific proposals so then
like for instance uh okay so the
workspace Theory they might come in with
the clim like no no you need the front
of the brain and so the question is well
what are we talking about exactly are we
talking about um phenomenal
Consciousness like the actual generation
of your experiences from moment to
moment or are we talking about your
knowledge your of experience your your
knowledge of your experience your
awareness of that you're ability to
report on them and contextualize it in
different ways well then you're probably
right the B is probably right that you
you need to get the frontal lobe in the
mix to do that although at that point
though by the time you're you're talking
about things like that you might even
need more than the frontal Lo we
actually might be in like an ex like a
extended mind account in terms of like
what actually goes into to be
self-reflective like you know we like we
we you know use like the environment to
like offload memory like the way like
where so you know the workspace the
global workspace or play Space might not
even be scul bound you know but still
the so yeah so the approach I took was
basically to say that um the different
theories were bringing important
contributions that all these brilliant
people that these are all brilliant
people who've given a lot of thought and
there have something important to say
then the question is are they may be
using words differently so like in that
debate earlier between like integrated
information Theory the global workspace
Theory you had this recent like adversar
collaboration
say but it's not clear they were using
the word Consciousness in the same way
like integr information Theory is
talking about experience like and
phenomenality Global workspace Theory
sometimes it's like illusionists
sometimes you know they're they're more
it's like more like a higher order
thought type Theory and and they're
oftentimes not necessarily but you know
it's it's usually they're talking about
you know um you say like conscious
access as opposed to phenomenal
Consciousness and
so so then the idea is that if you're
you try to be more like like what are
the precise claims that people are
making and you dig into them a lot of
the conflict might just be be
people not communicating enough and
saying like oh I meant this by that term
and you meant that oh and instead there
being just like one way we use words it
might be that like the different ways we
were using words had different
trade-offs and maybe like to come
together we have to like add qualifiers
so instead of like we try to say this
one word means this one thing maybe we
use like um we need to use like two or
three words to specify which World we're
in and what we're talking what what our
reference are and then the claim I make
is that once you do that um a good
amount of conflict actually is not as um
much as it seems like it needs to be
like you you're actually significantly
like these different theories are
actually to important degree and a
useful degree talking about different
things right right yeah well you know
maybe there's a psychological account of
the fact that scientists like at you
know they they might pretend that they
believe in collaborative um work but
there is there's a there's a tendency or
an in towards
adversarial boundaries which are often
incredibly constraining so no it's it's
a good point and I think it's a good
point as well about how much language
really shapes again I I don't mean this
in some sa wolf deterministic way but
shapes the way that we view these um
these models the way we view these
debates I mean I think the most I think
for me comes back to to what you're
talking about like right at the
beginning that I could look at a rock
and say well there's something kind of
going on there it's tracking some you
know it's doing some kind of variational
Basi and inference one of you know I
think the two most important words for
someone coming into the free energy
principle depends on the definition of
the free free energy principle you like
but my two favorite are looks like so
anything that has a Marco blanket and a
uh you know a steady state tractor
non-equilibrium steady stere tractor
will look like it's conducting basy and
inference and that look the the the
question of what it is doing the process
Theory really gets opened up once you go
oh the free principle is just you know
it might well just be a descriptive tool
and then we talk about active inference
predictive processing variational
message passing but I think this this
looks like notion is often um
forgotten and it's important to keep it
in the back of our mind
that yes there is something quite
miraculous about the coherence of a
stone um but I guess every theory has
its
Miracles um and the fre principle is not
it's it's not devoid of its axioms do
you think that's a kind of reasonable
thing to
say I think so and it's like yeah in
general we're trying to do is like you
know I guess would uh minimize the
number of like you know DX moach as we
need to call and the number of Miracles
and like but you we're need to like like
you mentioned like synthetic opary
categories like these things you need
some you need something to build with
you know or also in terms of like the
what we're talking about with like uh
evolutionary priors and like inductive B
like you need to start somewhere you you
need something must be granted you know
but but like but let's try to like do
the most we can with the least and so um
and but but still those things that you
um are granted you know in a way like
there's a sense in which like you they
might be like they're the preconditions
for proceeding it all those are the
Miracles we need to to go on and so
there's like we end up like uh it's like
for the case of like yeah like a rock
and you just say like you know it looks
yeah I had a section I put into like the
like original and and and and left it in
there maybe unfortunately like like the
like the iwt paper and I I I felt crazy
writing it but you know I think like if
I like emphasize this like looks as if
like it feels less crazy and then saying
the rock is engaging in basing inference
to exist you know but I guess you know
there's a you I guess you could say
there's a sense in which
like that's how it
is at that point I guess you're almost
in like a quasi tautology and that like
like let's okay so here's like the face
based description of the Rock and then
it uh I guess you say like if you keep
looking at it um well I guess all the
rock
though it might be we need something
like it might not work for the rock but
it might need the
like you need something where like that
density of the thing like like that you
can point to it and like there's a
combination like the solenoidal flow and
gradient flow where the thing is like
picking itself back together like a drop
of oil yeah like a drop of oil that like
like re that grabs itself and then yeah
yeah that yeah so once you do that is
that kind of like I guess that's Carl's
like 2019 paper then it's like a sense
it's like you can say like well that
actually is Basi inference yes that
there's like where you expect to find it
there's a thing like as a probability
distribution and then if you just look
at its action it's doing basing
inference and then like well is that a
tautology maybe but um uh it's a damn
interesting ony tautology and on yeah
yeah yeah no it's uh I remember hearing
Carl first on Lex freedman's podcast
talking about a drop of oil kind of my
first proper exposure to free energy and
I just like what I just couldn't think I
I I didn't believe that drops of oil or
rocks or molecules could be so
interesting and and you're right you
know um science I don't know who said it
but science is about making the familiar
unfamiliar um and we're certainly making
rocks and drops of oil pretty unfamiliar
when we're talking about then conducting
variational Bas and inference there's
someone who might be interesting to talk
to he wrote a paper on like the world is
neural network and so like I think he
would um potentially get to this issue
of like um is there just like a way in
which like um you could just make like
an like the ontological claim like the
the rock is inag like he like he would
do I think
a a good job of like making a case for
that potential okay cool I I'll check
out the paper I mean yeah I mean for me
this the question that I literally
started this podcast with still stands
which is if we take the drop of
oil it's it's it's kind of yes can be
seen as calculating a
posterior
um
but what does that mean like what does
that me like what is doing the
calculation and what's it doing a like
it what so the the P of itself given its
environment is just really high I mean
once you sort of break that down it just
becomes it it seems to me to just return
back to a descriptive account rather
than a uh process theory of what the
what the drop of oil is actually doing
so you know I think where a lot of
active inflence confusion comes from is
that we
can't um we can't we we we struggle
conceptually to get away from aties in
ego model when we're thinking about how
we are and how the world is so it
it's tempting perhaps to think that
there's a little homunculus within the
drop of oil grabbing itself together and
maximizing model evidence for itself but
even I would not say that no no neither
that was by the way I'm not saying that
either but it's um it might be tempting
for some let's um let's get to
psychedelics because you're at John's
Hopkins which is the kind of place to be
in terms of psychedelic research I think
a useful place to start not only for
myself for our audience is people might
have a sense of the history of
psychedelics in science um and the long
history and the taboo and the fact that
now these experimental studies are
taking place and the taboo is lifting
perhaps you could kind of give a uh
brief history if possible of the history
of psychedelics in science um you don't
have to go back to shamanic cultures but
if you feel so inclined I I Shan stop
you
I mean that actually is a
um I'm working on a paper right now of
like the Deep history of psychedelics
like um going both back to shamanic
cultures but before in terms of the um
evolution of the um signaling systems
that they appear to primarily act upon
uh in particular the um 5 ht2a seron
receptors and thein is a Agonist all
that receptor that particular receptor
class yeah and um so there there's a a
paper I just recently uh revised and
resubmitted um called uh um Albus or
alter beliefs under psychedelics which
um basically provide uh is it's
providing I guess you might say
heterodox account of psychedelics um
within Act of inference I read the
preprint so uh I'm I'm
familiar so so that's um so I guess
we'll get to that in a bit but this so
uh that's like where the focus has been
but the current paper would be like um
why is
it that we have psychedelic experiences
and like like what is it is there is
there like so you you might say um maybe
in a deflationary sense you could say
like like pink her would talk about like
uh music is uh cognitive cheesecake
where it's like you know if you try to
look for an Adaptive story about music
you could try but it's just like no
there isn't really one that's like that
meaningful it's sort of like you can the
Adaptive story of like cheesecake is
like it's a super stimulus that's
created because of this this and the
other but like there is no evolutionary
count of Cheesecake it's a late Comer to
the scene and so it's a deflationary
count of like music would be like
there's no specific music adaptations
it's just like a super stimulus we
create for ourselves you know uh because
of other things that we need and other
aspects of our cognition and so with
psychedelics you could say like you know
these drugs just happen to be like you
know a super stimulus that's like
created um you know maybe by plants to
defend themselves against predators in
terms of you know you don't want to
quite um you know
uh you know you want to um either repel
and so you know maybe like you know
breaking the good
regulation like like like making the
thing do anomalous infer inference could
be you know a good way of like um
repelling you your your Predators um or
you might want to potentially entice in
terms of you know there's like some
symbiosis that exist in terms of things
like that was it um reindeer um I don't
know if this has been established but
like you know um possibly like by
consuming things like um is it like is
it lyen I forget what it is but like
fungi like it might like help them to be
more like exploratory in certain parts
of their like seasonal cycle and so then
there's like a symbiotic relationship um
and you're actually enticing the
organism to come in
but the um yes so actually that's that's
a very Live question of like the Deep
history of psychedelics in the place I'm
going to I'm trying to go in this
upcoming paper is to argue that um you
know so the it seems like the receptor
system
itself um might have evolved I'm
claiming
um actually in a way so so um so the
count of
psychedelics in the frery principle I
think that's most wellknown would be
called the Reus model yeah relax beliefs
under psychedelics and the idea being
that psychedelics are relaxing your
basium priors and so with your prior
expectations relaxed you are now free to
think different thoughts and be updated
by the world experienc it more
profoundly and be changed by more more
profoundly and um so I've been um trying
to uh Nuance that account and saying
that like that might be
um part of what happens as part of like
very high degrees of 52a agonism and
that you do get something like that but
that might not be the cybernic
significance of the 582a system as a
control parameter um and that in in many
ways it might actually be exactly the
opposite and so they first evolved with
a uh Gene duplication event around the
Cambrian explosion around with the
Advent of JW fishes and so one of the um
speculations I make is actually and this
might be
um Predator prey arms races where
someone can basically if you can
specifically bite then this now like
adds fuel to um a certain fire of like
you know I can now go up and and
precisely swim and bite and kill and now
you have an interest in being able to
have that strong prediction that you uh
use to basically uh enslave your in
action and Achieve that goal um and and
the stronger you can make that
prediction the the the more you know
potentially within limits the the more
reliably you'll Converge on that goal as
opposed to doing something else but then
you might also have an interest on the
side of prey of uh not being the person
bitten sure and so this idea of like uh
turbocharging the organism um doubling
down on the priors potentially as a way
of allowing for a specific goal Pursuit
that might have been the original story
but where does this like Reus account
come in uh one of the speculations I'm
making um along it's it's a a paper I'm
writing in collaboration with Sue Carter
who uh studies oxytocin mechanisms um
and there's a follow-up paper I'm
writing with um before the other one was
published with um Matt Johnson but um is
that actually um orgasm and birthing
might have been the original psychedelic
experiences and that actually so you're
basically relaxing the priors about the
bounds of yourself and having greatly
elevated plasticity and capacity for
updating why would you want something
like this those would be two cases where
you'd want it whether it's bringing
basically two basically bringing either
a a letting allowing a a mother to care
for the child long enough to uh help it
to get past these ear early milestones
and also allowing potentially um uh
mating pairs to stay together long
enough to help these hungry children to
the
acceleration
okay that's that's G into that then
so what would the the kind so there's
some coupling going on here in terms of
this kind of
turbocharging it's Psych in a sense it's
kind of psychologically adaptive to have
relaxed belief over yourself over kind
of yourself model maybe even your
autobiographical self model um so as to
facilitate um the Advent of another
person into your life right so like
people just qualitatively talk about how
they now feel like this child is their
purpose they're kind of secondary to
this child in their life so what's the
kind
of what's the causal par for and what's
the chronology in this is it is it a
genetic adaptation that um occurs kind
of simultaneously with like modern child
birth is or whatever that looks like or
is it um does it predate it and then get
sort of exapted by um birthing star yeah
birthing or does it come later that like
what what I don't know actually how you
would examine that but what are you kind
of claiming in that
regard so the
specific um the specific mechanistic
Pathways that were canaly in which ways
uh we got no idea sure so forance like
uh um you know there's there all sorts
of things that could contribute like for
instance um
uh there seems to be for instance like
the the 2A receptor um you know in
general it's it's it's actually fairly
insensitive relative to something like
the 1A receptor but if you take it and
expose it to um like uh reduced like
blood acid like rather reduced blood pH
or elevated acidity through something
like uh hyperventilation like you know
some or things like um carbon dioxide or
lactic acid accumulating then it gets
potentiated and so like for instance
like you know during uh sexual activity
during um uh uh birth there will be a
lot of heavy breathing um uh over an
extended period and you know is that
actually like an accumulation of carbon
dioxide and actually that's part of a
mechanism of potentiating these
receptors maybe we have no idea could it
involve something like endogenous
DMT maybe we have no idea could involve
as Sue is arguing um uh oxytocin vas
supress in different combinations quite
possibly um but we we're just beginning
that now in terms of the specific
Pathways but the in terms of when this
might have occurred and some more things
that could have been important I'm
wondering if there were like a couple
waves of strong selection one probably
with like the Advent of um Mamon uh
reproduction in terms of like and Mamon
care so so the um you know once you're
now having to going to earlier like
don't eat your child care for it you
know once you're getting to and and
youve seen a lot of rodent species it's
actually you know a little bit uh
tenuous that process right like like the
run to the litter often gets eaten you
know you're not that far from like the
atavistic state of kind of
like of um so to get this interest like
U was uh I think Pat churchin will
actually talk about like an extension of
like self grooming to down so for
instance you can maybe think of like
actually like relaxing body maps and
then making them plastic for a Time on
the occasion of birthing or like for
instance like during nursing and then
like basically if you then include um
the pup into the body your Offspring
your body Maps like that could get in
count like that off the ground um or
then once like for instance the um to
the degree you get um parental
investment you know but this would then
be like a a mamalian story and any of
those species there might have been
strong selection on like these like
protos psychedelic Pathways and then you
know for and then for humans you know it
would be like all the things coming
together in terms of um having uh you
know the these big brains extremely
vulnerable hungry Offspring which you
have to care for for a long time
oftentimes also needing you know more
than one because part of it also of the
Care is providing um you know protection
within the social hierarchy teaching
them things you know two heads being
better than
one and so having the you know the
bonding of the parents for the child and
the parents to each other like now the
selection pressure might be really
strong what was selected you know
something involving oxytocin essentially
in connection with DMT with other we got
no idea but wow then I guess the one
more thing that could happen in um not
just in humans but maybe particularly in
humans is our um our ability to like
like was it Jonathan talks about like
the hive mind switch like our ability to
actually like have Collective
effervescence and to come into like a
group a sense of group identity for the
sake of basically uh um uh doing things
according to Fashion including beating
out other groups and so there seems to
have been strong selection on that in
the human case also and so the claim
would be that these like
basically pressures for inter subjective
uh coupling being particularly strong in
humans might have been a source of why
for instance um uh psychedelic
experiences
uh we're probably not the only species
to have them um but the idea being that
um at least the reasons that we know
that we are sensitive to them some of
that could be because of that history of
selection because of those challenges of
of of bonding between mating pars
between parents and children and
potentially between uh
tribe yeah that that is really
really um it brings two things to mind
um one is I don't know whether you've
ever heard of the obral
Dilemma um which is basically this idea
that when humans went from being
quadrupedal to
bipedal the hips of the mother narrowed
and what was happening is there was a
lot of uh stillborn deaths a lot of
child birth deaths because the hips were
narrowing but the size of the baby's
head stayed the same so a lot of
children Dy in um child birth a lot Ms
mothers were dying in child birth and so
there was an evolutionary tradeoff
between um early
birth and
bipedality and so what actually happens
is is that children start to get born
younger pregnancy is reduced in time to
to permit the narrowness of the hips
that allows for
bipedality which in turn sets the stage
for for
caregiving and the fact that a child
can't just pop out of the womb like a
gazelle and go running so that's the one
thing that comes to mind I'm gonna
include that in the next paper well give
me a shout out um and then the second
and then the second thing that makes me
think of is maybe this care domain this
fundamental need to expand body models
self models could be this kind of
Consciousness synthetic a priority we
were looking at maybe there's an
Adaptive pressure to
feel this kind of Selfless Love Agape
whatever you want to call it towards
your Offspring so as you know for
evolutionary reasons so that you are a
caring uh altruistic
caregiver
that's I think potentially
very important for like so
this in the evolution of cogn modernity
there seems to be a kind of like chicken
egg story or site dilemma where um you
know so like chsky like you know you
know talks about language for the
service of thought but like so I guess
that he somewhat sidesteps his dilemma
by saying like language is just useful
for structuring thought right from the
GetGo um but like let's say like you
aren't quite thinking that ways and like
language is about communication like At
first like you are you think you need
that to get like language use off the
ground well then the question is like
um but if you need language use to like
who are you communicating to and so like
something that could basically um
uh
scaffold
um so so in terms of like the the um
elaboration of uh forms of Consciousness
and maybe like the even potentially like
the Precision and the and the uh I don't
if You' say richness but like like even
consciousness like phenomenal
Consciousness in its qualities its
ability to you know uh represents like
precise things
like it it seems like in kind
of it seems
like if there's like a
use to being able to feel your feelings
in a way where you can reflect on them
in a way where they can meaningfully uh
uh impact your behavior um if if that is
helping to um basically provide some of
the selection
uh for
certain I don't just thought works but
for certain complexifications of
Consciousness that that could
potentially help other places where you
might have chicken egg problems like as
a source of pre-adaptation like I guess
is what I'm wondering yeah exactly I
think that that's exactly the line kind
of shooting down yeah I mean this is
yeah wonderful wonderful ideas I guess
another question that comes to mind is
when people think about psychedelics
they probably don't think about relaxed
basium priors they think about tripping
for on of a better word they think about
hallucinations Visions auditory um
hallucinations as well so in terms of
the sort of adaptive
self-organizational um
yeah uh functional utility of
psychedelics that will Mak sense where
on Earth do uh the sorts of uh Magic
dwarves or uh recurrent patterns or
whatever Terrence McKenna was talking
about what what's going on there and and
how does that complexify this story so
um so before we get to machine elves so
part of the heterodox psychological view
uh uh rather the heterodox active
inference on psychedelics um would be
that um potentially those types of
phenomena as hallucinations or some
forms of like you might say psych
psychotic cognition or like the the um
you know the entertaining of of a of a
thought that you would not normally
under entertain you might think to be
crazy under other circumstances but that
is there live in your mind that you can
maybe think of in some ways it seems to
have like almost the shape of a
schizophrenic delusion or like a Proto
psychotic
delusion so um you could potentially
argue for these as a relaxation of
highlevel constraining beliefs allowing
those to be free form but you could also
think of those as particularly strong
priors also that you're imposing onto
the world and not rather you're now
saying I'm gonna I think this is there
this is my expectation and I am not
going to let that be contract
contradicted by sense data and so that's
so there's an interpretation also in
terms of a strengthening of belief of
those phenomena you mentioned and one of
the points I'm trying to make in the
paper is I don't think we know how to
think about this and so it's it's
probably some complex like ad mixture of
relax and strength and beliefs both
directly and indirectly in different
combinations um where I'm I guess trying
to say the like um rather than ever
saying like psychedelics do X I want to
replace that with um this
psychedelic uh this particular compound
at you know roughly at you know this
range of doses does this to this kind
this kind of person with this kinds of
set and settings and the idea of saying
that like but the idea of like taking
inspiration from Reus is like relax Bel
being an essential feature in some ways
and looking to adjusting of your priors
and your mind is this like Leaf
ecosystem as a fruitful way of like
contextualizing psychedelic functions
but then saying um moving beyond relaxed
beliefs talking about like both strength
and relax in direct and indirect ways
but to come along to uh DMT elves that
would be like an example of like um you
know so you can say uh you know uh you
could maybe think of that in a relaxed
belief story and that for instance uh
know elves do not exist and now I've
like relaxed certain aspects of my
ontology and now I've like made room for
these imaginings to arrive in a vivid
form like because of like um of an
indirect because I relax beliefs at this
high level of certain core schemas that
like tell me what I should expect in the
world now I've made room for psychedelic
elves for instance or like you know
entities you could also tell a story
though that these are actually um kind
of coming back to core knowledge you
know things like um uh um uh agood or
agency or things like
um but maybe not even core knowledge
like just early lessons in the learning
curriculum and on Ong goinging ones of
just we expect agents in the world
because that's the primary thing we're
encountering that's our primary niche as
each other and so then basically for the
beliefs so like in a strengthened
account you could say let's say you're
strengthening your beliefs maybe that
you're the you're getting a direct
strengthening of these Prime these
priors for agency detection are they
evolutionary priors are they
developmental priors we have no idea you
know in my thinking they tend to be more
developmental but it's you know it's a
spectrum of how you know where you
how how how much Evolution shaping went
into them and but as as our conversation
earlier um yeah also I I stumbled across
uh you saying just these words which
really call my eye archetypes as call
priors and I thought oh that's
fantastic what a what a lovely way to
put it I mean okay I this is just this
is really really cool um really exciting
I guess guess so so just to piece
together to scaffold together the
chronology the causality the
phenomenology let's just like try and
put it all back together so if the
original psychic experience let say was
uh child birth or
orgasm how does this end
up uh is it just a is it just a
coincidence that this ends up in
Plants
um and
if it
is is it informative that it was
happening in child birth or um orgasm or
is that just kind of a as I was saying
like a coincidental feature of the
activation of this
receptor um because your you the
argument that you said there which
earlier which is that is a kind of
defense mechanism or a kind of uh
attractor toward symbiosis is quite
convincing I guess we have to fold into
all of this
the shamanic cultures and then the kind
of more modern therapeutic lens on
psychedelics is there a way of
coalescing those seemingly disperate
strands so like for
plants like there's the
impact that these signaling
molecules these different ones would
have on the plan itself and then on the
other systems that interact with them so
for instance the um you have the 1A and
the 2A receptors will tend to have uh
different impacts on cytoskeleton
Dynamics and so let's say you want to do
something like a
phototaxis like like that actually it
seems will involve some um I'm
remembering correctly I should remember
this precisely but um there might even
be like you can think of it like um
changing the cytoskeleton Dynamics to
allow for greater fluidity you can maybe
think of that as like a kind of belief
relaxation for Mo morphogenetic
inference of the plant so it's like you
can you can think of the plant as like
you know you doing a phototaxis and say
no I'm here now I'm there you maybe you
think of that as like a kind of like um
uh updating for the plant itself and and
maybe that's even part very
speculatively of why like you find it in
something like a cactus where like
that's actually kind of a harder thing
because you're block here and like you
know something like that but then the
other aspect would be the defense and
another reason you might have it in
something like a cactus is because like
if you're in the middle of the desert
and you're
juicy you're extra tasty you know like
in terms of like there is a lot of game
there there are a lot of you know
contenders in town for things to eat
there's actually plenty everywhere but
still you're you're you're a Target and
you're stationary um by and large you
know so then like you know the which
Predators were they targeting you know
like like insects um you know uh what's
happening to the belief Dynamics in the
insect and so you know at that level you
know maybe you know it's largely a uh uh
um a Rebus account of of like these 52a
agonists for the
insects potentially in terms of like
changing uh their normal behavior I'm
not sure how you would think of their
but like the idea like you know someone
you know nibbles on you um it might be
good for them to uh go away become more
exploratory and and maybe even um mate
like crazy like you actually see
something like this in like uh locusts
um they have they're colonized by
hallucinogenic fungi which seem be part
of their mating cycle and is part of
this like period of intense mating they
undergo and so you know you know you
know the question is like why not just
poison them you know maybe it's just
like this was like the best poisoning
came up it was good enough and it just
did the job it it arrived by some means
and just the form of poisoning is um
taking the the model the organism has by
which it is adaptive you relax that
model but that's not necessarily a good
thing for that that that that insect
especially you know with his body weight
you know it's eating a lot of it and so
the idea of that that insect you know if
it's if its models are really altered
and if those models are trying to
constrain all the different ways that
system can bifurcate to like be more
homogenous as response and adaptive ways
um you don't come out necessarily ahead
by doing that adaptively and so that's
just the way um insects figured out or
their plants figured out how to protect
themselves um is and and the point is
the attack uh but maybe it's not even an
attack um maybe it's like you want um
you know it's you it's fine if you
nibble on me just don't nibble too much
and then uh but just go away and then um
and pre and and then if if we had this
nice relationship of you don't bother me
too much um you know maybe I even like
you to be around maybe I even like that
I facilitated your mating and I like
that your genes are more prevalent in
the Next Generation so yeah I guess and
then coming to you know Shaman well
before before you do just I'm curious
about what you think about this because
just to like add maybe a a technical en
this I'm curious about what you think
from a Rebus account in in this case you
mentioned exploratory Behavior there or
epistemic foraging which I thought was
really an interesting illusion because
in both cases you offered there there's
a move towards epistemic Behavior either
whether it's mating and or you know go
away in an aversive manner or go away um
and basic like the reindeer example you
know spread me around basically in in a
kind of weird
way right yeah yeah yeah
whates go forth right and what that
screams to me is so just in in the sense
of like the actual computational
modeling in pom DP schemes is an
emphasis over expected utility would be
sort of high Precision over your B and C
schema um and and e as well your prior
uh your prior overaction your habits
basically and maybe what's happening
here again it's a completely nent fault
that I haven't given much obviously uh
you know fa to is that rela you're
relaxing your prior beliefs about the
consequences of your action thereby
making every single possible action
policy equal in terms of epistemic
utility which means that you then Maxim
you do some sort of jany and
maximization of entropy which makes the
best uh in terms of just the um expected
free energy formul makes the best action
policy that which maximizes Information
Gain and all uh test model parameters so
I'm wondering whether that speaks to in
terms of a kind of technical unpacking
of what might you know what might be
happening at a very um low level here
with insects and
cacti it was fit well um with like
changing migration patterns I think it
would fit really well with that um in
terms of uh like like think of like
human use cases it seems like it's a
mixture like so for instance like um so
like um sometimes you know specifically
would be for um you know breaking out of
some State you're caught in like you go
to the shaman and this is part of it but
but oftentimes it would be like with a
very specific interest in mind like um
who someone cursed my cow who is it you
know or like but or or sometimes it
would be like um uh uh so sometimes it
seems like it is a good amount about
like the epistemics in terms of about
like trying to maximize learning and
breaking you free from like the thing
that is usually owning you from within
you know like your usual way of
achieving your goals keeping you stuck
in a certain pattern and then it's like
you need to learn something different
but how are you going to learn something
different if you're always doing the
same thing again and again and so yeah I
I think that fits for a lot of the like
a lot of the healing uses that a company
like like an iasa ceremony that that
seems like a good description but there
like other use cases like for instance
like in um like um think it's Amazonian
tribes like uh it's actually like
specifically pragmatic and that like
they do it to to get the hunting party
together and like they'll um they're
about to go to war with a specific other
tribe but then you could also though
make a case of like um you know is it
that like
their like their goal of what they want
to do when they encounter the other
tribe you want that to be presented in a
very Vivid form and that imagining you
want that counterfactual to be hyper
precise so that becomes actual or is it
um more like a matter of like this kind
of collective effervescence from earlier
and you actually want a Rebus account so
that before you go into battle you're
basically you know all one body
coordinating together fighting you know
having each other's backs um or both and
you want you know an early stage of
something Rebus like and then maybe a
later stage of something more uh
involving belief strengthening so it's
like sometimes you're letting go of the
pragmatics and sometimes you're actually
like holding on to the the um pragmatic
values specifically zooming into it um
it seems like there like at least in the
human case there is no singular account
but in terms you're saying about like
things like um uh like the the case of
like migration patterns in an animal
being changed um that seems like that
that that the relaxing the pragmatics
allowing the epistemics to to more
optimization for that that that could be
a really important part of that I think
cool amazing yeah I mean we haven't got
too much time left but um I guess two
more questions one totally trivial the
other one not trivial at all so I'll
start with the non-trivial one um I
Hawkins you're you're really at the
heart of the current uptick in
psychedelic research are
you well just to frame this I sense from
an external perspective there was a
great deal of
excitement you know starting five six
seven years ago and maybe now there's a
um there's a slight conservativism
that's crept in and and and saying okay
the the psychedelics might not be the
Panacea that we hoped it might have been
seven or eight years ago again I'm not
on the inside I don't know but that's
just my
instinct what what are your kind of uh
predictions expectations level of
optimism with respect to psychedelic
therapy in the next 10 20 30
years
um I have some
uh so if we can avoid the very live
possibility of uh backlash as um uh
adverse outcomes happen inevitably and
they will be more notable you know like
with driverless cars like if you know
even if unet they're saving lives you
will note those cases where it just
slams into you know a person and you'll
just be and that'll change everything
and so it doesn't take many people to
have some really bad
experiences um you even see like with
the re like Matthew Perry like what
happened with him Al and and that really
is um actually
really deeply responsible for everyone
involved because um I don't want to say
that you know like ketamine's you know
uh not a mixed uh like it's powerful
medicine and but uh in that case like um
you you see the shape of it there's
already like people are interpreting
this as oh ketamine is dangerous and
already this is causing people to call
for more of a of a pullback but he was
also on a a good dose of an opiate um
probably had some drink system and was
in a hot tub so you know so it's like um
you know did he die of respiratory
depression and then drowned you know
it's uh but so things like that can
happen and uh it doesn't take many of
those for the Psychedelic Renaissance to
really be like pulled back in ter
potential like lifechanging uh medicines
interventions um oh by the way uh
whenever I'm speaking it's um outside of
a h Hopkins position they and they are
um so speaking from the outside um they
have a particular role I'd say in in the
Psychedelic Renaissance of doing largely
conservative work within a mainstream
medical model and trying to say can we
push forward that and and and and how
can we approach these medicines safely
and responsibly and so um they tend to
be I'd say more conservative in what
they're doing and it's a very valuable
function um and and so uh you know in
general they try to be very careful I'm
I'm a little less careful um so
uh the
um some of the things that are so some
of the open questions and challenges we
have is what
um I guess you say business models or
how can we scale psychedelic therapy so
I so one of the problems with like like
a psilocybin um intervention is they're
amazingly expensive and so the question
is like how can we get like broad access
to them you need some sort of like group
therapy and like a different model than
the ones we currently use just to make
the economics work to make this like an
available one a widely available
intervention um the other question is
like if you remove some of the um
expectancy effects you would get from
like the places where these
interventions were done and like um you
know the you know having it done in
John's Hopkins you know like the um or
the Good Friday experim you know and Har
there's a certain trust and Authority
which is interacting with this as part
of like leading up to it that's part of
like the expectation that you will be so
changed and so if you then try to you
know have clinics opening up everywhere
do you get the same effect because
you'll have you know the reports you
know is some of the five most meaningful
experiences in a person's life a few
sessions your life has changed and to
what extent can we still get outcomes
like that um as we move into basically
scaling and and having more institu ions
in more context and do so safely one of
the things I'm actually very excited
about is I have some uh friends in um
Pharmaceuticals who are basically
creating analoges of these psychedelic
compounds to try to change their
property slightly and so one of them is
like for instance um uh shortening their
duration of action well why' you want to
do that well let's say like you could
show up for a therapist and you can do
basically MDMA therapy and be sober
again in two hours m
and so that would both allow you
basically to do it um more flexibly do
it uh and do it more times potentially
and you know and with less risk from the
dose because things like cytotoxicity
will be a function of both the dose and
the duration of effect and so if you
reduce that duration of effect things
like you know um metabolic strain you
would reduce it so those advances I
think going to be a complete GameChanger
like uh the these short acting powerful
compounds
I think Psychiatry will not be the same
once those are on the scene and just
lives will be saved and transformed
fantastic so yeah and so there's a lot
like things are very fraud right you
know we could have something like a
couple bad outcomes could cause like a a
chill on the whole thing but the promise
if we could just make it through this
Crucible I think it's unbelievable like
amazing well that's exciting and then my
uh my super trivial question especially
even more trivial given that response is
um iasa is uh famously kind of an enigma
um because it's you you may correct me
on my uh chemist my biochemistry here
but isn't it
DMT mixed with a plant among the
hundreds of thousands of plants that are
found or could be found in the
Amazon what's your Joe Rogan esque
thoughts on how on Earth they managed to
s emphasize iasa hey you have your your
edible TMT but that'll be broken down in
a hot minute and so you need to find
basically this monomin oxidase inhibitor
to keep it going but among all the
different things you could have tried
how did they find the right one quite
yeah the shamans will will to tell you
the plants told us that's how they did
it that doesn't help um I guess you know
I'm hoping I don't know maybe we should
get like Joe Hinrich on the job and like
basically some sort of computational mod
of like the process of like trying out
the permutations of like what shamans do
normally uh maybe it's actually
tractable in terms of like if you see
just what they're doing it's like yeah
they were going to find that given what
they were doing in like over over 200
years you would expect this percent that
they found it sure so I would expect
something kind of like that or maybe the
plants told them well maybe the plants
told yeah maybe Adam that was that was
amazing I'm kind of mind blown um that
was awesome thank you so much I I mean
with every guest I always feel like I
learn just infinite sums of new
information which makes this so much fun
for me um but no I really thank you I I
know you're a busy man and so I'm very
grateful for you giving me two hours of
your
time um it was a pleasure we're going to
we're going to keep digging away at
these questions um but yeah for me and
the insute yeah it was it was an
absolute uh pleasure on my part so thank
you again thank you all right that is